<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://apache.org/forrest/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Features</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section>
      <title>Technical Features</title>
<p>Simetron uses the .NET platform and runs on Microsoft Windows, Linux and MacOS using the <fork href="ext:mono">Mono runtime</fork>. The software is written in C# and the user interface is built using the <fork href="ext:gtk-sharp">Gtk# widget toolkit</fork>.</p>

<p>Once completed, Simetron will provide the following technical features:</p>

<ul>
	<li>Plug-in framework ala Eclipse.</li>
  <li>A graphical road network editor that can import background orthographic aerial pictures as well as DXF files (and indirectly ESRI Shapefile or ARC/INFO files containing GIS data). The editor provides drag and drop, zooming in and out, copy and paste, and most of the common modern user interface paradigms.</li>
  <li>Highly scalable parallel simulations.</li>
  <li>Graphical interface to visualize running simulations, and playback mode for visualizing saved simulations.</li>
  <li>Graphical reporting of simulation results via desktop application and web browser. Reports are available in PDF format and include charts and graphs.</li>
  <li>Multi-user and multi-site.</li>
</ul>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Functional Features</title>
<p>Simetron provides default plug-in modules that allow modeling intersection constraints at different levels: fixed capacity constraints based on the percentage of turning movements; variable capacity constraints based on fixed traffic signals; dynamic capacity constraints based on local/centralized traffic control plan(s).</p>

<p>Simetron allows explicit modeling of public transportation, and it includes plug-ins for transit lane allocation, automatic transit traffic signals, and timetable management.</p>

<p>Simetron provides plug-in extensions to allow integration with external OD estimation models, disaggregation models and routing models.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
